<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Codified Musings</title>
 <link href="http://codifiedmusings.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://codifiedmusings.com/"/>
 <updated>2015-01-15T22:27:38-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://codifiedmusings.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>Jordan Haines</name>
   <email>jordan@kalosal.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Profound Leadership</title>
   <link href="http://codifiedmusings.com//leadership/profound-leadership.html"/>
   <updated>2014-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://codifiedmusings.com/leadership/profound-leadership</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;profound-leadership&quot;&gt;Profound Leadership&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you had the opportunity to share a team with someone who doesn’t speak often, but whenever they do it’s absolute gold?  Maybe they’re an expert in a specific field and only weigh in when the rest of the team is approaching a challenge entirely wrong.  Or maybe their thoughts are consistent, well-timed and include much needed humor.  In any case, when this person speaks, they are listened to.  Their thoughts are anticipated and valued by the team at large in a way that no-one else’s seem to be.  This person is (ever so subtly) profound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good leader is also profound.  Not always - but certainly when it matters.  And this balance - being profound when necessary as oppose to just another voice in the discussion - is very hard to maintain.  Leaders who try to be profound with each thought expressed will quickly find all of their words lose power.  Leaders who refrain from those riskier insights that may benefit the group can lose respect and influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the ability to interject a profound thought at just the right time is a skill worth honing.  In leading a variety of groups, I’ve found that there are some situations which afford a better foundation for a profound thought than others.  Recognizing these situations is key in providing  as much value as possible to a team through personal insight.  This may involve providing a summary of thoughts multiple team members have expressed, introducing a new perspective or even making some executive decision in light of an ongoing discussion.  Each of these actions - and the many more that a leader could take - can easily be derailed if the team is not ready for profound leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering all of this, it seems that honing one’s ability to “be profound” can be difficult!  As leaders, we want to weigh in on every issue.  We want to help our teams whenever possible and provide as much perspective as we can muster.  While this is great (and the passion is important!), maybe it’s not always the best approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-sweat-the-little-things&quot;&gt;Don’t sweat the little things&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this goes without saying, but not every team discussion is worth a profound thought.  While I would hope that a team of surgeons explores all options and perspectives before discussing options with a patient, the same profound leadership is probably not necessary when trying to decide on a pizza place for dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This philosophy also applies to more practical discussions within a team.  Petty discussions are - quite frankly - not worth the energy required to interject with a breakthrough insight.  Leaders who fail to realize this try and lead their teams through every little decision which is frustrating and quickly becomes ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;let-the-teamwork-itself-out&quot;&gt;Let the team work itself out&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing seems to beg for profound leadership like a team in stark disagreement.  When leading in such situations, it is so tempting to scramble for some sort of “let’s all be friends” or “everyone’s correct” insight.  While there are times where this is appropriate - especially if the discussion starts to get personal - there is also something to be said for letting the team work itself out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, if discussion is respectful and - well - happening, it may be best to just sit back and watch. All teams are ineffective sometimes.  The best teams have just had more opportunities to practice being effective.  And one of the best ways to practice being effective is to work through a solidly ineffective situation.  As a leader, coddling your team and negating such an experience could actually hurt in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;youre-not-the-only-leader-hopefully&quot;&gt;You’re not the only leader (hopefully)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Profound leadership is great; profound leadership from an entire team of people is effectively bliss.  Thus, it’s important to give all team members the chance to be profound leaders themselves. It always seems to be the team member you’re least expecting who shines the most in the face of great challenge.  If this person is always overshadowed by hasty insights from other leaders, the team as a whole is missing out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there are some team members who can be consistently relied upon to provide insight in specific areas.  Maybe Joe knows everything about fire safety and can provide the perfect perspective on risk with a new project.  Or maybe Susan actually knows all of the best pizza places around and can pick the perfect one for a midnight snack.  In either case, there’s safety and comfort in allowing these team members to show their strengths.  Providing lesser (though sometimes seemingly more profound) insight would be a disservice to these team members and the group as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choose-your-battles-wisely&quot;&gt;Choose your battles wisely&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;#### What you’re passionate about is what really matters and what you’ll be most effective in discussing.
Inevitably, the areas where you will be able to provide the most valuable insight are those areas you are most passionate about.  Passion is both hard to mask and hard to fake.  As such, it is best used to your advantage as what can set your insight apart from the drone of other thoughts bombarding the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a thought arises that genuinely makes you smile or - better yet - thoroughly excited, you’d best express it.  Quickly.  The team will appreciate the well-timed insight as much as your profound leadership in delivering it to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes being profound is seen as the sort of “magic” of leadership.  It’s the ability to provide a voice when it’s needed and a thought when it counts most.  However, how often profound insights are appropriate depends almost entirely on the team that one is leading.  While there are strategies for recognizing when you - as a leader - can be most effective, they pale in comparison to the effect that individuals can have on a team and it’s reception of your insights.  The best teams will adapt to the style of a truly effective, profound leader in the same way that the leader’s insights come to fit the team.  How do you provide profound leadership?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mirrors</title>
   <link href="http://codifiedmusings.com//leadership/mirrors.html"/>
   <updated>2014-07-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://codifiedmusings.com/leadership/mirrors</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;mirrors&quot;&gt;Mirrors&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently finished&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Paper-Towns-John-Green/dp/014241493X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1406612737&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=paper+towns&quot;&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Paper Towns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/a&gt;by John Green; it’s an excellent book but you probably already know that given how popular it is.  Alternatively - if you haven’t read a fiction book in like over a year, you’re doing yourself a extreme disservice.  It’s summer - pick up a good one, I promise it will be worth your time.  I used to be like you, until I read this book that is, and now I’m happy enough to write a blog post about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, in &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Paper Towns&lt;/span&gt; there is quite a bit of talk about mirrors.  Mirrors that are much greater than you’re typical reflective rectangle in that they reflect an image of who &lt;i&gt;you&lt;/i&gt; really are.  This type of mirror affords the rare opportunity for (near) clear introspection.  Because a traditional shiny rectangle would hardly be up for such an abstract task, this type of mirror is a person.  A friend, some would say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this to be a remarkably interesting concept, and one that relates rather beautifully with my own idea of leadership.  A leader - or at least anyone who hopes to continue being a leader - is able to change.  Leaders mature, leaders grow and leaders gain perspective that furthers their own ability to relate with and understand others.  This - conveniently enough - allows them to lead a team of humans, who - by nature - change, grow and learn all of time as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process of positive growth would be impossible without a really good mirror.  Whether it’s a new sense of humor or a new way to treat a teammate, it is very important that leaders are able to see an accurate picture of how incremental changes in one’s self actually manifest.  Good leaders need an impactful, objective way to wrap their head around themselves in the same way that good leaders empathize with and understand those that they lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the friend comes in.  But not just any friend.  We’re talking about the type of friend who understands you on levels you have yet to discover exist.  This is probably then friend you’d go to when life gets real; the friend who knows not only what to say but how and when to say it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the friend who can reflect you.  And the better they are, the better you’ll become.  As you grow as a leader, you’ll be able to see yourself (albeit through the perspective of this mirror) and actively reflect on the person you’re becoming. Like what you see?  Forge ahead!  Is some part of your reflection a little different than expected?  Not a problem - luckily you’ve got this awesome, reflective friend to help you work on…you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously there’s no way that this mirror is perfect.  It’s not like a traditional mirror that just reflects light back at you - pixel for pixel.  No, this mirror is jaded and enhanced by the very person who comprises it.  Because of this, it’s all too easy to disregard the image put forth by your mirror.  Maybe they’re jealous or they let political beliefs get in the way.  Maybe they’re jaded by religion or blinded by issues they, too, are struggling with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or maybe - just maybe - you have one of those mirrors that you can without a doubt always trust.  Now this is a valuable mirror.  If you trust your mirror, then you trust it’s reflection of yourself.  And, if you have a trustworthy conception of yourself, you’re in an incredible position to shape, refine, grow and enhance the one person in this world who is you.  Cool, huh?  Who’s your best mirror?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Leading By Example</title>
   <link href="http://codifiedmusings.com//leadership/leading-by-example.html"/>
   <updated>2014-07-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://codifiedmusings.com/leadership/leading-by-example</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;leading-by-example&quot;&gt;Leading By Example&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In your own words, please describe what defines an effective leader”.  This was the question asked of dozens of candidates I had to opportunity to interview for a leadership position recently.  The question is intentionally generic and truly standout answers are usually the mark of an effective leader.  Almost all of the answers, however, involve some element of: “A good leader leads by example”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve all heard this before.  While the concept of leading by example is nothing new - it nonetheless seems to be important and accessible to everyone.  Without much exception, the &lt;i&gt;best&lt;/i&gt; leaders always seem to lead by example.  So what does it mean to lead by example?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the basics: what exactly are these leaders an example &lt;i&gt;of&lt;/i&gt;?  Digging deeper, there seems to something about these individuals that the rest of us want to emulate; there are some qualities they embody that we feel are worth being held up as an example to our teams, peers or even society as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One quality that I inevitably find in those who truly lead by example is a strong sense of personal leadership.  These individuals are willing and able to effectively stand up for what they believe in.  They are able to express themselves with integrity.  These leaders have convictions and morals that they hold themselves to, even when no-one else is watching.    This is exemplified in the manner with which they consider all decisions; hard choices are made only after the opinions and personalities of all those who will be affected are carefully weighed.  In such cases, a leader’s personal preference is emphasized no more than any other team member’s as it truly is no more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way a personal leader is courageous.  A personal leader trusts the desires and sentiments of those she is leading because she fully understands them, even if she does not agree with them.  Further, such leadership requires empathy - an ability to relate with and come to know those you are working with so as to gain the ability to better understand how outcomes or situations will affect each individual personally.  Finally, without fail, personal leaders exude passion.  They have a passion for their own beliefs and a passion for the people they are leading.  Governing both of these is a heartfelt understanding that each individual’s passions and beliefs are just as important as the next if for no other reason than each has a person associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a personal leader is one who is able to effectively stand up for herself and her team - including their beliefs and convictions - with integrity, time and time again.  A trait of someone who leads by example is the ability to do all of this personal leadership stuff in a way that is respected, admired and (indeed) actively emulated by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, I’ve found that someone who leads by example is about so much more than just getting stuff done.  At (severe) risk of becoming too vague, those who lead by example are really just model human beings.  For this reason, these leaders aren’t always correct and don’t always come up with the right answer - a human never would.  These leaders make mistakes and then react appropriately, responsibly and respectably.  These leaders are proud of and happy for others when they see success, even if it is in light of the leader’s own mishap or failure.  In short, someone who leads by example is truly devoted to her team and those individuals who comprise it.  She respects these individuals the same way (and certainly no less) than she respects herself.  This is what provides the foundation for a beautifully cohesive, effective and joyous team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, those who lead by example are so often not &lt;i&gt;trying&lt;/i&gt; to be leaders.  Instead, they are just trying to be friends, family, teachers or students.  They just happen to be so darn good at it that they inspire the rest of us to reflect, step up our own game and become better people in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I guess to answer the question, those who lead by example are simply consistent models of really good people (about what you’d expect, right?).  They are worth emulating, they are worth following and they are always an inexplicably fulfilling joy to merely be around.  Who leads you by example?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Those who lead by example are simply consistent models of really good people.  They are worth emulating, they are worth following and they are always an inexplicably fulfilling joy to be around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hello World - The start of something good</title>
   <link href="http://codifiedmusings.com//leadership/web_dev/hello-world.html"/>
   <updated>2014-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://codifiedmusings.com/leadership/web_dev/hello-world</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This post was orginially written to inaugurate my blog - Codified Musings.  Since then, my focus has shifted a bit but the general sentiment remains: I write because it’s enjoyable and helps with my own understanding of the world.  I suppose others may read this - which would be awesome, but is not necessarily my intention.
I’ve considered revising this post many times; the writing style does not much my newer posts and I really find it slightly embarrasing.  Nonetheless, this musing is codified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I first had my first urge to start blogging; it’s nice to finally be putting words to the page.  I’ve learned an immense amount, in a variety of fields, from blogs of individuals far more ambitious than I.  There’s something to be said for the ability to discover a thought then so thoroughly discover and explore it so as to create meaning for others.  As we enter an era where information is so readily accessible, there is great value in the ability to take vast, gooey gobs of information and produce some sort of simple, tasty meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I’ve always found writing therapeutic, I look forward to blogging as a means to better understand my own thoughts and musings.  Whether it’s a cool algorithm from class or a challenge on a current development project, thinking through concepts to the degree of explaining them to others seems like a great way to cement my own understanding.  Call it selfish, and perhaps it is, but I do hope to share thoughts and practical development techniques that serve value to many.  I think it’s beautiful and remarkable when a person can synthesize information and express ensuing thoughts in a manner that doesn’t inform or educate as much as inspire others to pursue their own intellectual adventures in a similar field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these formative thoughts, I’ve decided to take a more active role in this important and thoroughly entertaining process of creating information for the 21st century (I figured we could use some more…).  This is not something I seek to do alone; indeed - my best thoughts are unmistakably influenced and bettered by the perspective of others.  I will strive to give credit where credit is due in these scenarios both for the sake of professional credence and to better connect the wealth of information that’s otherwise frustratingly impossible to parse.  To me,   I’m sure that over the course of writing, a number of these people will making guest appearances in the thoughts I express.  In addition, I am genuinely excited for the many more that I will inevitably find while searching for the perfect perspective to best inform an idea I’m creating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having concretely made the decision to start writing - and having expressed the inspiration for doing so - I suppose that what remains is the question of what to write about. I figure I should probably just write about those topics that best  capture my passions.  Currently, these topics are computer science (with an emphasis on web development) and effective leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer science is fairly self explanatory; there are a number of high level concepts and theories that I find thoroughly captivating and look forward to exploring publicly.  Specifically, I love algorithms and artificial intelligence because both have such far reaching implications for high level problem solving and understanding of interactions with the world around us.  I know I’m not alone in finding beauty amidst the most elegant solutions to the most complex problems.  In studying computer science, I’ve had the fortune of being able to take incredible classes taught by some of the most inspiring thinkers of our time.  This has been marred, however, by the misfortune of having too little time to thoroughly study, explore and enjoy the content I find irresistibly intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective leadership - on the other hand - is a concept and quality that I’ve come to respect, admire and strive for through experience in various leadership capacities over recent years.  “Leaders” are so much more than individuals with positional power or vast responsibility.  A leader is any individual who takes an active role in some social environment.  A leader has objectives and ideals that are larger than himself; others are necessary to fulfill the vision of a leader and it’s the leader’s responsibility to not only orchestrate the efforts of others to realize these abstract ideals, but to simply communicate these ideals to the group as well (which can be exceedingly difficult).  Through recent observation and practice of leadership in a wealth of scenarios, I’ve made some realizations that have better informed my own concept of a leader.  I’ve found that there are positional leaders who have some innate structural power to be exercised with strategy and precision.  There are those who excel in leading by example - doing what they believe to be right even in the most trying of circumstances.  There are leaders who seem magical in their ability to inspire and encourage others to find exciting individual potential that had previously gone entirely unnoticed.   And the list goes on.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest leaders, however, are some winning combination of all these “types” of leaders.  Truly great leadership unnoticed.  Well…almost unnoticed.  Working with such a leader leaves one brimming with fulfillment, a sense of achievement and inspiration beyond words.  A great leader can’t help but create (through inspiring transformative thought and realization in others) new leaders who are very effective in entirely different ways.  It is an art as much as it is a talent carefully grown and tuned through years of experience.  An effective leader (by my own assertion) is this breed of great leader with the added requirement of actually getting things done.  An effective leader and - more importantly - those she works with, achieve their objectives and further their ideals in a demonstrable and often measurable manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these loose targets for the writing to come, I very much look forward to producing more thoughts that - if nothing else - will be fun to think!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
